{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man wrote against slavery in one city's Gazette under aliases like \"Vindex\" and “Candidus.” Following the arrival of the Dartmouth this man and James Otis distributed the \"circular letter\" to organize a meeting at Faneuil [[FAN-yoo-il]] Hall. Many years after his best known action, this man succeeded John Hancock to become the fourth governor of Massachusetts. For ten points, name this Founding Father and leader of the Sons of Liberty who orchestrated the Boston Tea Party.",
      "answer": "Samuel Adams"
    },
    {
      "question": "This polity's ruling family came to power after its scion, Francesco the Malicious, captured its chief fortress while disguised as a Franciscan monk. In 2015, the prince of this polity apologized for its role in the deportation of 90 Jews during the Holocaust. That prince is the child of this country's Prince Rainier III and American actress Grace Kelly. The Grimaldi family has traditionally ruled, for ten points, what wealthy city-state on the Franco-Italian border known for its yearly Grand Prix?",
      "answer": [
        "Principality of Monaco or Múnegu",
        "or Principauté de Monaco",
        "or Prinçipatu de Múnegu"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Pliny the Elder, a red stone named after this deity was able to reflect images. According to Homer in the Odyssey, this deity was “loved more than any place on earth” on the island of Lemnos, which was traditionally the cult center of this god. An altar dedicated to this deity is sometimes referred to by the people of Elis as the altar of “warlike Zeus.” The Chalceia [[chahl-KAY-ah]] festival, in which \"peplos\" garments were woven from a loom, was dedicated to Athena and this deity. For ten points, what deity was the primary target of worship for Greek blacksmiths and craftsmen?",
      "answer": "Hephaestus or Hephaistos"
    },
    {
      "question": "A representative from this state was accused in 2021 of violating the Mann Act by transporting a minor across state lines for \"immoral purposes.\" In 2022, this state's governor was caught on film saying \"we gotta stop with this Covid theater\" after children wore masks during a press conference. In March 2022, this state passed a law that barred teaching an elementary school \"LGBT\" curriculum with the \"Don't Say Gay\" bill. For ten points, Matt Gaetz and Ron DeSantis are politicians from what Southern U.S. state?",
      "answer": "Florida 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "A fixture on the Rouen [[roo-EHN]] Cathedral is known as the \"[This Commodity] Tower\" due to having been built by churchgoers who gave up this item up for Lent. Propagandist Joseph Goebbels stated, \"One cannot shoot with [this commodity], but with guns\" in a speech justifying peacetime rationing. A challenge by Napoleon III to invent a substitute for this foodstuff for the poor led to the invention of margarine. Described by Pliny as \"the most delicate of food among barbarous nations,\" for ten points, what is this dairy product made by churning?",
      "answer": [
        "Butter",
        "Butter Tower"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Teenagers dressed like this man and formed neighborhood gangs in a namesake 1950s subculture in the Belgian Congo. A Beatles song inspired by the \"Bungalow\" version of this man asks him, “What did you kill?” In the musical Annie Get Your Gun, this man attempts to persuade Annie Oakley to join his company in the song, “There’s No Business Like Show Business.” For ten points, what American showman was famed for his cowboy- themed Wild West show?",
      "answer": [
        "Buffalo Bill or William Frederick Cody",
        "Buffalo Bill's Wild West"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Sailors from this city established the port of Parthenope [[par-THEH-noh-peh]] in Magna Graecia, eventually becoming modern Naples. Ancient theories on why eclipses occur are outlined in The History of Astronomy by Eudemus [[YOO-deh-muss]], a philosopher from this city. Ptolemy III offered to rebuild a bronze statue which collapsed into this city-state's harbor due to a 226 BCE earthquake. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state off the coast of Anatolia that possessed a wonder of the ancient world, the bronze Colossus.",
      "answer": [
        "Rhodes or Rhodos",
        "Eudemus of Rhodes",
        "Colossus of Rhodes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The historical \"Sultanate of Women\" period began due to the influence of this man's wife, Roxelana. Despite an overwhelming troop disparity, this man's forces failed to capture the island of Malta in 1565. This man succeeded Selim the Grim and warred with the Safavids under Tahmasp I. This victor at the Battle of Mohacs [[MOH-hahtch]] was later repelled at the 1529 Siege of Vienna. For ten points, identify this sultan of the Ottoman Empire known as “The Magnificent”",
      "answer": "Suleiman the Magnificent 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this kingdom, Savoyard mason Master James of Saint George built a ring of fortifications, including Beaumaris [[boh-mah-REH]], following the passage of the Statute of Rhuddlan. Rhys Gethin [[REES GEH-tihn]] and a national hero of this kingdom, Owain Glendower, defeated the forces of Henry IV at the Battle of Stalling Down. A ruler of this region's kingdom of Powys [[POW-iss]], Llywelyn [[loo-ELL-in]] the Last, swore fealty to Edward I following the English conquest of this modern country. For ten points, name this constituent country of the United Kingdom whose name appears in the Princely title of the heir to the English throne.",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Wales or Cymru",
        "Prince of Wales",
        "Kingdom of Powys before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Sarah Hopkins Bradford wrote two biographies of this woman, including Scenes From the Life of [this person]. This woman led the forces of James Montgomery in the Raid on the Combahee Ferry during the U.S. Civil War. In 2016, in a decision that was later put on hold, Treasury Secretary Jack Lew announced that this woman would replace Andrew Jackson on the front of the twenty-dollar bill. For ten points, name this abolitionist and Underground Railroad conductor who was known as the “Moses of her People.”",
      "answer": "Harriet Tubman or Araminta Ross"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This geographic feature was named after an American who died from a head injury in Panama. A quest to find golden ore led to the immortalization of this feature after a pilot and his companions spent eleven days descending the tepui in order to reach the nearby village of Kamarata. The El Río Caroní, a Flamingo monoplane atop Auyán-tepui [[ow-YAHN teh-PWEE]] near this geographical feature, was finally recovered more than 30 years after it crashed. For ten points, what geographical feature in Venezuela is the world’s tallest uninterrupted waterfall?",
        "answer": [
          "Angel Falls or Salto Ángel",
          "or Kerepakupai Vená"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While on his quest to find the city of El Dorado, what explorer possibly became the first European to view Angel Falls? Earlier this English statesman founded the failed colony of Roanoke.",
        "answer": [
          "Sir Walter Raleigh or Walter Ralegh",
          "Editor's Note: surname is spelled differently in various sources"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Leonid Pasternak's charity poster of a wounded soldier leaning against a wall next to the phrase \"Aid to War Victims\" became an anti-war symbol. Alexander Samsonov killed himself after losing the entire Second Army in this war, during which Russia suffered losses at the Masurian Lakes and Tannenberg. The Treaty of Brest- Litovsk withdrew Russia from, for ten points, what war whose devastation led to widespread popular support for the February Revolution?",
        "answer": [
          "World War One or First World War",
          "the Great War"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Tsar of Russia sent a series of telegrams to his cousin, Kaiser Wilhelm II, affectionately dubbed \"Nicky,\" in a half-hearted attempt to avert World War One?",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These things were first theorized by George Johnston Stoney as a “fundamental unit quantity of electricity.” A theory created by John Dalton depicts the water molecule without these particles while a model created by Erwin Schrödinger presents these particles as “matter waves.” Robert A. Millikan’s oil drop experiment was successful in measuring the charge of this particle. Discovered in 1897 by British physicist J. J. Thomson, for ten points, what is this negatively charged particle integral to quantum physics?",
        "answer": "Electrons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "J. J. Thomson created what “model” that depicts negatively-charged electrons immersed in a positively-charged space, named for the dessert it resembles?",
        "answer": "Plum Pudding model 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was the third-born child of a group of nobles called the \"Illustrious Generation.\" Cartographers including Jehuda Cresques [[yeh-OO-dah KRES-kess]] and Pedro Nunes [[NOO-ness]] were hired by this man to convene at his alleged School of Sagres [[SAH-gresh]]. This man's personal shield bearer, Gil Eanes [[AINES]], made numerous failed attempted to pass Cape Bojador [[boh-HAH-dor]]. Supposedly sponsoring several expeditions to Madeira and the Azores, for ten points, who was this Portuguese prince known for his attempts to map the west coast of Africa?",
        "answer": [
          "Prince Henry the Navigator or Infante Dom Henrique, o Navegador",
          "Infante Dom Henrique"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry the Navigator utilized what recently-developed, lateen sail-equipped ships in his expeditions?",
        "answer": "Caravels or Caravela"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A group of U.S. sailors taken prisoner in this country gave the middle finger in a publicly-distributed photograph, claiming to their captors it was a \"Hawaiian good luck sign.\" This country had the Bauhaus-trained Konrad Püschel redesign the damaged city of Hamhung. Holding up to 114,000 spectators, this country's Rungrado 1st of May Stadium was the largest stadium in the world until 2020 and featured events such as the Arirang Mass Gymnastics Festival. For ten points, name this Asian peninsular country that fought a war with its southern neighbor in the early 1950s.",
        "answer": "North Korea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "North Korea's first president was this Communist leader who founded the \"Down with Imperialism\" Union.",
        "answer": "Kim Il-sung"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Lauzun’s Legion unhorsed Banastre Tarleton during this battle. Wilhelm of the Palatinate-Zweibrucken [[ZVY-broo-ken]] captured Redoubt Number 9 during this battle, while Alexander Hamilton captured Redoubt Number 10. French forces under the Comte de Rochambeau supported American troops during this battle, which led Lord North to proclaim, “Oh God, it’s all over.” For ten points, name this last major battle of the American Revolution, which led to the surrender of Charles Cornwallis.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Yorktown",
          "Siege of Yorktown"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This French admiral defeated British forces at the Battle of the Chesapeake, leaving Yorktown without needed supplies and reinforcements.",
        "answer": "Comte de Grasse or Francois Joseph Paul de Grasse 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer's son, Maxim, supported the controversial book Testimony, which Solomon Volkov claimed were this composer's memoirs. A theme from a symphony by this composer, which inspired a song from Franz Lehar’s operetta The Merry Widow, is repeated twelve times to depict a Nazi invasion of his country. An article in Pravda accused this composer of Formalism, after which he wrote his D minor Fifth Symphony. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the Leningrad Symphony.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich or Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shostakovich's 13th symphony takes its name from a poem by Yevgeny Yevtushenko [[yehv-too-SHEHN-koh]], which itself is named for Babi Yar, the site of the Nazi massacre of over one hundred thousand Jews in what Ukrainian city?",
        "answer": "Kyiv or Kiev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This war was declared by one side in part due to a wave of negative publicity toward the concentration camps overseen by a commander known as \"Butcher\" Weyler. Leonard Wood commanded one unit during an assault on Kettle Hill during this conflict, though he was overshadowed by his second-in-command, a former Assistant Secretary of the Navy. For ten points, name this late nineteenth century war during which the Rough Riders captured San Juan Hill, part of a campaign to take Puerto Rico from a European power.",
        "answer": "Spanish-American War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The U.S. war effort in the Philippines was assisted by this revolutionary who became the first and youngest president of the Philippines.",
        "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo y Famy"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Robber Barons",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Gilded Age Robber Barons, name the man who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founded Standard Oil and is widely considered the wealthiest American of all time.",
          "answer": "John Davison Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known as \"The Commodore\" and made his fortune in steamship lines before forming the New York Central railroad.",
          "answer": "Cornelius Vanderbilt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resolved the Panic of 1907 with his personal wealth and helped consolidate U.S. Steel and General Electric.",
          "answer": "J. P. Morgan or John Pierpont Morgan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as president of both the Central Pacific and Southern Pacific Railroads and founded a university near Palo Alto.",
          "answer": "Leland Stanford or Amasa Leland Stanford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founded the American Tobacco Company and endowed a university in Durham, North Carolina.",
          "answer": [
            "James Buchanan Duke",
            "Duke University"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted to corner the gold market with James Fisk, leading to the 1869 Black Friday panic.",
          "answer": "Jay Gould or Jason Gould"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a Canadian-American nicknamed \"The Empire Builder\" and controlled the Great Northern Railway and the Northern Pacific Railroad.",
          "answer": "James Hill or James Jerome Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Survived an assassination attempt during the Homestead Strike and made modifications to the South Fork Dam leading to the Johnstown Flood.",
          "answer": "Henry Clay Frick 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Warsaw Pact Leaders",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Warsaw Pact, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leading country of the alliance that formed the Iron Curtain in Eastern Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union or Sovetsky Soyuz",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "or Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik",
            "or USSR",
            "or CCCP",
            "or SSSR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Carpathian nation that was overrun by Warsaw Pact forces following a revolt in its capital of Budapest.",
          "answer": [
            "Hungary or Magyarország",
            "Hungarian People's Republic",
            "or Magyar Népköztársaság"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Czechoslovak city whose liberalizing \"Spring\" was crushed by the Warsaw Pact.",
          "answer": [
            "Prague or Praha",
            "Prague Spring",
            "or Pražské jaro"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Genius of the Carpathians\" and Romanian dictator who was executed by firing squad on Christmas in 1989.",
          "answer": "Nicolae Ceaușescu ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German First Secretary who approved the building of the Berlin Wall.",
          "answer": "Walter Ulbricht or Walter Ernst Paul Ulbricht"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Communist Albania whose move toward Maoism caused a full break with the Warsaw Pact.",
          "answer": "Enver Hoxha ] or Enver Halil Hoxha"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest-serving national leader in the Warsaw Pact, leading Bulgaria for 35 years.",
          "answer": "Todor Zhivkov or Todor Hristov Zhivkov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last leader of the Polish People's Republic who implemented martial law in the early 1980s.",
          "answer": "Wojciech Jaruzelski or Wojciech Witold Jaruzelski 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Dead Languages",
      "prompt": "Concerning some dead, dying, and endangered languages, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Language of the Roman Empire, whose Ecclesiastical form is still used by the Catholic Church.",
          "answer": [
            "Classical Latin",
            "Ecclesiastical Latin",
            "or Church Latin",
            "or Liturgical Latin",
            "or Italianate Latin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language family spoken by a few indigenous people on Hokkaido, Honshu, and other Japanese islands.",
          "answer": "Ainu language or Ainuic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Language family of northwestern Europe that included Gaulish, Gallaecian, and Brittonic.",
          "answer": "Celtic Languages"
        },
        {
          "question": "Semitic language of the Levant that is commonly called the \"language spoken by Jesus.\"",
          "answer": "Aramaic or Aramaya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Romance language named for a region of the Adriatic Sea coast whose last speaker died in an explosion near Dubrovnik.",
          "answer": [
            "Dalmatian",
            "Dalmatic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language of southwestern England which was revived by linguists in the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "Cornish",
            "Kernowek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arawakan language once spoken in the Greater Antilles originating words like \"barbecue,\" \"tobacco,\" and \"savannah.\"",
          "answer": "Classic Taíno"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-spoken mode with which the newly-revived language of Silbo on the Canary Islands is communicated.",
          "answer": [
            "Whistle",
            "Whistling 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist worked under John Randall's biophysics unit while on a three- year Turner & Newall Fellowship at King's College London. An article titled “The Structure of Viruses as (20 pts)",
        "Determined by X-Ray Diffraction,” was the last publication of this scientist. Raymond Gosling, a student working under this scientist and Maurice Wilkins, captured Photo 51, an image (10 pts)",
        "critical in understanding molecular structure. For ten points, name this woman who was influential in discovering the double-helix structure of DNA."
      ],
      "answer": "Rosalind Franklin or Rosalind Elsie Franklin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This body of water, home to the Eora and Tharawal people for thousands of years, is the location to which Maggie May is sent after “robbing a homeward bounder\" in a Liverpool folk song. Arthur Phillip was assigned to establish a British (20 pts)",
        "colony at this location but opted to settle at Port Jackson. James Cook initially referred to this location as “Stingrays Harbour,” (10 pts)",
        "and this body of water was his first landing site in Australia after sailing from New Zealand. For ten points, what bay in Sydney did the British establish as a penal colony?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Botany Bay or Kamay",
        "Stingrays Harbour before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many of this artist's surviving illustrations are collected in the Codex Arundel and the Codex Atlanticus. Giorgio Vasari may have painted over a lost painting by this artist of four men riding raging war horses during the Battle of Anghiari. Christ (20 pts)",
        "holds an orb in his left hand in a painting by this artist that sold at auction for $450 million in 2017. This artist likely chose a noblewoman from the Gherardini family as (10 pts)",
        "the subject of his one of his best known paintings. For ten points, name this painter of Salvator Mundi and the Mona Lisa."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leonardo da Vinci",
        "either underlined portion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's curtailment of the power of the \"Hundred and Four\" who controlled the Miat council led to his exile. After a task force led by Titus Quinctius [[KWIN-tee-ooss]] Flamininus [[flah-MEE-nee-ooss]] discovered his location in Bithynia [[bih-THIH-nee-ah]], this general (20 pts)",
        "ingested poison according to Livy. Earlier, this brother of Mago won several devastating victories at Lake Trasimene [[trah-see-MEH-neh]] and Cannae [[KAH-nay]] before being defeated during a counter-invasion of (10 pts)",
        "North Africa. Scipio's victory at Zama led to, for ten points, which general's defeat in the Second Punic War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Hannibal Barca 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author wrote about George Norris's tour of Nebraska in an analysis of his filibuster of the Armed Ships Bill. Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist Arthur Krock helped redraft this man's thesis, \"Appeasement At Munich,\" into a book examining the failures of the (20 pts)",
        "British government to take steps to prevent World War Two called Why England Slept. In that book by this author, he analyzed figures including Lucius Lamar, Thomas Hart (10 pts)",
        "Benton, and Sam Houston. For ten points, name this author who included eight biographies of U.S. senators in his book Profiles in Courage."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John F. Kennedy or John Fitzgerald Kennedy",
        "or Jack Kennedy",
        "JFK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's time as a barrister included his handling of the \"Caucus Case\" involving supposedly rigged municipal elections in Bombay. He's not Woodrow Wilson, but this man proposed his Fourteen Points in response to the Simon Commission. Stanley Wolpert's biography (20 pts)",
        "on this man became the basis for a 1998 biopic which controversially starred Christopher Lee. In the Lahore Resolution, an organization led by this man called for the creation of a (10 pts)",
        "Muslim state separate from India. For ten points, name this leader of the Muslim League and founder of Pakistan."
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad Ali Jinnah or Mahomedali Jinnahbhai"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A mass meeting of tenant farmers in this state at the Helderberg Mountains resulted in the Anti-Rent War, whose leaders were charged with rioting by Amasa J. Parker. A governor of this state became a leader of the Hunker faction against the Barnburners and (20 pts)",
        "later negotiated the Gadsden Purchase as Secretary of State. A president from this state established a \"Regency\" named for its capital whose members included William Marcy. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this state, the birthplace of Martin Van Buren."
      ],
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After his victory at the Battle of Mount Algidus [[al-GEE-dooss]], a semi- mythological character returned to this occupation after a stint as dictator. The Lex Manciana of North Africa was a 2nd century edict which regulated the maximum number of (20 pts)",
        "tenants in this job and how many days people in this occupation, which included Cincinnatus, needed to (10 pts)",
        "plow per month. The writer Columella wrote On Rural Affairs concerning, for ten points, which profession responsible for producing crops?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Farmers",
        "Farming"
      ]
    }
  ]
}